Hi. You've learned the process
of crafting a narrative
about your project,
and you've learned
how to visualize
key data points that help
you to tell that story.
Now it's time to
bring it all together.
In this video, we'll highlight
some useful presentation
techniques.
Think about one of your
favorite public speakers
and why you enjoy their
presentations so much.
Is it their voice,
their knowledge,
or the confidence they
exude while speaking?
Brene Brown is one of
my favorite speakers.
She's widely known
for her 2010 TED Talk,
The Power of Vulnerability,
which received 60
million views worldwide.
Brown didn't begin her
career as a public speaker,
but as a research professor
at the University of Houston.
Today, she uses public
speaking as a way to
teach executives and leaders
about courage and empathy.
Public speakers spend a lot
of time working on their craft.
Speaking to an audience—whether
to inform,
entertain, or share—isn't
always easy,
and data alone isn't enough to
convince people that you've
made the right decisions or that
your project was impactful.
An effective presentation
helps convey
the important work that you and
your team are accomplishing
on your project.
And throughout the project, you'll
likely have many opportunities to
present—from your
initial kickoff meeting
to your weekly status updates
to your final project
presentation.
As you begin to craft
your narrative,
think about your audience.
Ask yourself: What do I
want my audience to know,
think, or do as a result
of this presentation?
Create your presentation around
the big picture, and
keep it simple.
Now let's discuss three ways to
help you give an
effective presentation.
Those are being precise,
flexible, and memorable.
First, to give an
effective presentation,
you need to be precise
about your key points.
Identify the problem you're
solving for your audience and
remove any content that
dilutes your narrative.
One way I ensure that
my slideshow presentations
are as precise as they can
be is by using a technique
called "designing
for five seconds."
The idea is that your
audience should be
able to understand a slide
within five seconds.
So I keep my presentation
slides simple,
including only the most
relevant data points, to avoid
overloading my audience with
text they don't
have time to read.
To give an effective
presentation,
you also need to be flexible.
Flexibility is a huge part
of your job as a project manager.
For example, it's possible
that a stakeholder
may have to leave
your presentation unexpectedly or
that other attendees
may arrive late.
Consider the approach
you'd take if you had to
shorten your presentation
from an hour to 30 minutes,
or even just five.
Know the most important points
you want to make, and be prepared
to share only those points,
should the unexpected occur.
Preparing ahead of time also
helps you be more
flexible when presenting.
Ample preparation
helps you to avoid
small mistakes that can
potentially distract
from your narrative,
like stumbling over sentences or
struggling to pull up a
slideshow presentation.
To prepare ahead of time,
you might practice delivering
your presentation to
members of your team
and invite them to
offer feedback,
ask questions, or share concerns.
Preparing ahead of time also
gives you space to
identify and come up with
answers to the types of questions
your audience might have
about your presentation.
It also gives you time to
imagine and prepare for
possible objections
your audience might
have to the decisions
you want to make.
Lastly, be memorable.
Develop a strategy that helps
make your narrative
unforgettable.
Think back to effective
storytelling.
This is the point
where you want to
tie in your data analysis,
effective visualization, and put
the finishing touches on
your narrative to
bring it all together.
Use stories or
include repetition to
help your audience remember
the information moving forward.
Another helpful tip is to be aware
of your body
language when presenting.
Maintain an upright posture
and rest your hands at your side.
When making a point, try
elevating your tone of
voice for emphasis.
Pace yourself by using
intentional pauses and
speak about half
the speed you would
normally speak while keeping
your sentences short.
Make eye contact with
your audience and keep
your facial expressions
warm and friendly.
Finally, have confidence.
You've done the
research and are well-prepared,
you can set your worries aside.
If you're precise, flexible,
and memorable, you'll give
a great presentation.
Now that you've analyzed the
data and crafted your story,
your job is to present
your findings effectively.
Use these tips to deliver
a presentation worthy
of a standing ovation.
In the next video,
we'll wrap up and
review what we've
recently learned. I'll
meet you over there.